All right.
Good morning, Mr. Short. You're here on behalf of Democracy Action
Incorporated, is that correct?
Yes, I am. Yes.
Excellent.
Good morning to you all
Welcome along to the committee this morning. We've received your submission.
We have 10 minutes set down for you.
I'll hand over to you for introductory comments, and then I'm sure there'll be
questions from members. Thank you.
Thank you. Can you hear me okay?
Yes.
Well, thank you, Mr. Chair and members of the committee, for the opportunity to
appear today on behalf of Democracy Action.
As you would have gathered from our written submission, while we support trade with
India, our principal concern is the provision in the New
Zealand Free Trade Agreement with India affirming
the United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples, or
UNDRIP.
We have received correspondence from the Minister of Trade, the Honorable Todd
McClay, stating that the reference to UNDRIP in the agreement
is not legally binding and does not impose any legal obligations
on New Zealand.
And while we welcome that assurance, we do not believe that is sufficient.
Our concern is that the agreement formally affirms UNDRIP in
legal and constitutional terms affirmation is significant.
It signals an acceptance of a commitment and can influence how courts and
decision-makers interpret legislation and develop public
policy.
An express affirmation by New Zealand in an international agreement gives UNDRIP
additional standing that it would not otherwise have.
For that reason, we believe ministerial assurances alone are not
adequate.
For instance, ministers change, governments change, and
legislation endures.
We believe nothing less than a clear statutory prohibition will provide the
certainty that the Parliament intends.
And fortunately, the solution already presents itself in the national interest
analysis that accompanied the agreement.
Section 6 explains the new legislation and amendments to
existing legislation are required to implement the
bill and the agreement, and these measures will
be contained in a single ominous bill.
We therefore respectfully urge this committee to recommend that the implementing
legislation include an explicit provision stating
that the agreement affirmation of UNDRIP does not give UNDRIP
the force of law in New Zealand,
it does not create any rights or obligations under New Zealand law,
and it does not give UNDRIP the presumptive weight in interpreting
legislation,
and it does not make UNDRIP a relevant consideration for courts, ministers,
public agencies or other decision-makers.
For the avoidance of doubt, we further recommend the legislation state that for all
purposes of New Zealand law, policy, and administrative practice,
the agreement's affirmation of UNDRIP is to be disregarded.
Such a provision would remove uncertainty,
give effect to the government's stated intention that the reference has no
domestic legal effect, and prevent unnecessary litigation over
Parliament's intent.
We noted in our original submission
that Rosemary Banks at the United Nations,
when UNDRIP was put forward
under the, uh, instructions of Helen Clark at the time,
said that they would not sign it for the very reasons that have been
outlined in our submission.
So we'd ask the committee to make these
recommendations to the government.
Thank you very much for your time.
Excellent. All right. Do we have questions for Mr.
Short in relation to his recommendations?
I mean, very briefly, just at your oral submission here, you said that
legislation endures. In fact, legislation can be passed very quickly
in this Parliament, so I'm not quite sure that your statement that
parliamentarians come and go and legislation endures is correct.
Is that a question?
Well, governments change and then governments make decisions, don't they?
And they can change things. So it would be good to have that in place.
Thank you.
Okay.
So in relation to those clauses, sorry, did you have a proposal on where they
should be
im- implemented or inserted specifically?
Uh, yes, we had. That's in our submission under Section 6.
Under Section 6 of?
Sorry.
Under Section 6 of the,
um...
Let's get the wording for you.
It's in the national interest analysis which accompanies the agreement, Section
6 of that.
Yes. Yeah, sorry, I mean in the legislation.
Did you have a view on where that should go?
No. I, um, I'll leave that up to the people who draft the legislation, but it's
appropriate that it goes in there.
Okay.
We're not actually asking for the, uh,
Free Trade Agreement to be re- renegotiated.
What we're saying is that in the supporting documentation that
it should be included in that so it makes clear reference that
UNDRIP has, has no effect on the New Zealand legislation.
Okay. So just adding those specific five
recommendations as clauses within the enabling legislation
to avoid any uncertainty.
That's correct. Thank you.
Okay. Very good. Any further questions for Mr. Short?
All right. Thank you very much for your time this morning. Appreciate that.
Thank you. I appreciate the
opportunity to, to present. Thank you.
Okay. Next up, Export New Zealand and Business New Zealand
Good morning.
Morning.
Good morning, Chair. Good morning, everybody.
Morning. All right, welcome along.
You know well how it works, so I'll hand straight over to you for your 10
minutes.
Sure.
We've received your written submission.
Thank you. I've just got a very short two-minute introduction-
Sure
... and then looking forward to questions.
Thank you, Mr. Chair and members of the committee.
My name's Katherine Rich, Chief Executive of Business New Zealand, and
joining me today is Josh Tan, Executive Director of Export New
Zealand. Thank you for the opportunity to appear in support
of Business New Zealand and Export New Zealand's submission on the India
Free Trade Agreement Legislation Amendment Bill.
Business New Zealand and Export New Zealand strongly support this bill
because it contains the legislative changes needed for New Zealand to
implement the India Free Trade Agreement.
We encourage the committee to recommend that the bill proceed
so that the agreement can enter into force as soon as
practicable.
Business New Zealand and Export New Zealand have consistently
supported closer economic ties with India for
many, many years. We've previously presented our
views on the agreement itself. Today, our focus
is the legislation before the committee and the importance of
implementing it without unnecessary delay.
From a business perspective, certainty and timing matter.
This bill provides the legislative framework needed to give effect to the
agreement and allow New Zealand businesses to begin accessing the commercial
benefits. A powerful example of why this agreement matters
is for the New Zealand's fish and seafood industry.
After Australia secured preferential access to India, its fish
and seafood exports grew
269%, while New Zealand's exports fell by
67% over the same period. Under the
NZFTA, the current 33% tariff on fish and
seafood exports will be phased out over the next seven years.
Sheep meat and wool exporters, along with many others, will benefit
from immediate duty-free access, significantly
improving our competitiveness
relative to Australia. We recognize
that no trade agreement is perfect.
There are areas where we would like to have seen more ambitious
outcomes, particularly for dairy.
Nevertheless, the legislation enables an agreement that is
commercially meaningful, strengthens New Zealand's relationship with one of
the most important growing economies, and provides a
foundation for future improvements.
Our submission makes three recommendations.
First, that the committee support the bill.
Secondly, that it progress through Parliament without delay.
And thirdly, that the implementation is supported so
exporters can fully utilize the opportunity the agreement
creates. Thank you, and Josh and I welcome your questions.
Wonderful. Thank you very much.
Questions from members. Honorable David Benson.
Thank you very much for the submission, very clear.
Yeah.
The agreement
includes a commitment to investment.
Your members will probably be at the forefront of that.
What advice are you giving to them, and how many have indicated that they are
going to invest in India?
Yes, you ask a very good question because free
trade agreements are the start, and from there, it's how
we utilize and make sure that businesses take
advantage of that. So the message from Business New Zealand and Export New Zealand
is that we in the business community work extremely
hard to make sure that we get on planes,
send more delegations over, look at the market so we
can access that 700 million odd
growing middle class that wants our products
and services.
Just to supplement to that. How many have indicated that
they are going to invest in India?
We don't have an actual number,
but the feedback has been very positive.
Most businesses that are export-focused looking at India
understand the complexity of the market and the difficulty, but they see it
as a long-term play, and many have started to put
it into their export strategy. So Josh, do you wish to add?
Just feedback from our last barometer survey was that there was a
sharp increase in the number of businesses that were interested in looking at
India. I think from the discussions that we've had
in and around the country
, the market, because there has been quite high barriers in India, hasn't been an
opportunity which exporters have looked at for the past
several decades. Now that the free trade agreement is coming
into play, there is an opportunity for them to start looking there.
So it is a long-term game for us.
If I might add to that
. Because we were put at such a competitive disadvantage in
relation to Australia, there have been some that have
shifted product from that market because they just simply could not compete.
I think there is now an opportunity for some of those businesses to look back to
India now that there's more of a level playing field.
Vanushi Walters.
Thank you, and thank you both for your submissions.
So I know you represent 76,000 employers and
businesses, and your previous submission to
consideration of the treaty, it's appended, you spoke about not
holding any concerns regarding the labor mobility
provisions. And I wonder if you could speak a little bit more to that and whether
there are specific industries that are particularly appreciative
of those settings in the trade deal.
Yes. We looked at-
Very carefully at some of the comments being made publicly, and really
did a deep dive into that area with regard to immigration
and access to skills. And Josh has got some comments
to make from that from our immigration specialist.
So unfortunately, our
policy manager couldn't be here with us today, but she said that mobility
provisions are a normal part of trade agreements.
The business case is about enabling services, trade, skilled movement,
business establishment, and commercial relationships, and that New Zealand
does retain immigration policy control here.
So we're quite confident that
the mobility provisions are within the means of normal trade
negotiations.
Very good. Yes, Dr. Wilson.
My question is not about immigration.
Under the investment, there has been some concern from a number of people I've
spoken to that we're quite prepared to share our
intellectual property with the likes of kiwifruit, our own cultivars
that we've developed over years. We now notice also that India has got
a very strong dairy
sector,
partially perhaps because we've shared intelligence and
technology with them in the past. So there's a
fear that with this new commitment to investment, a
lot of our IP is subject to that as well.
Have you found that?
Look, we respect the testing of ideas through the parliament
and the different perspectives that are brought to bear in this discussion.
But we don't share those fears, and particularly with regard to
the dairy industry
in India, we don't see that as a competition to New Zealand
dairy farmers. Although, I think when you look at the sophistication
of our industry here, yes, we do have some things to share
around the globe. As
we expressed,
there was disappointment, of course, that this FTA does not
have significant dairy provisions in it.
But we see this FTA as the beginning of a relationship that can
develop over time, and we'd like to dream the big dream that over a period of time,
that we can have those opportunities in there.
Yeah, supplementary to just
now flipping to horticulture and the idea that we're sharing our IP
that's been grown in development through the likes of
Food and Plant New Zealand, et cetera.
Is that something that you might be worried about because number are-
We're not sharing IP for-- Are you suggesting we're sharing IP for free,
or we're undertaking-
It's part of the investment
... commercial
It's part of the investment commitment
... activities there.
Yeah. We looked also very carefully at the investment commitment,
and it is an ambition to promote
ongoing investment in India. And that
actually makes sense because we sign these agreements not so much to
have
events and cut ribbons. Governments
sign these agreements,
but it's the exporters that walk through the door and decide what
within a country they can do to expand
trade. So it's an ambitious target, but I think
businesses are increasingly talking about the opportunities, and at least we're
on a level playing field with our main competitors.
Had we not done that, we would never catch up in that
market.
Do you have confidence that the
proposals outlined around the protection of IP, I think
it's Annex 14A from memory,
in terms of ensuring that no IP
transfer happens until there is an appropriate system in country.
Do you have confidence that that will give certainty or
appropriate protections to any New Zealand exporters?
Look, I imagine when businesses are looking to do
business, protection of IP
and making sure that you can protect what
is special about your business is
something that all businesses do consider.
You don't go and do business with someone if you feel you can't protect your trade
secrets or your IP. So these will be the sorts of things that
business weighs up when looking at trading
with those markets.
But most businesses consider India as a very long-term
play. Business relationships are absolutely key, and you
only develop those over time. But IP is something that you would be discussing
as part of any contractual arrangements.
And certainly, those who are there
consider these issues daily. Josh, anything to
add to that?
What's up from Financial Alters?
I was just wanting to confirm, just because Dr.
Wilson suggested that there was a
commitment to share IP as part of the investment clause of the
agreement. I don't believe that that's the case, and so I just wanted to confirm.
It was an area of, that's
why I was asking-
Yes
... in terms of free sharing, that's not something that we-
That's right
... read into it.
Yes.
The
business will, as always,
look at export markets, make judgments
about the ability to serve those markets, and then go through every
aspect of the business plan to make sure everything from IP protection
through to
labor through to margins, ability, supply-
Mm-hmm
... you name it, are part of that plan.
Sure.
But overall, we see it as a terrific opportunity, and at least we can play catch up
with Australia.
Very good. Well, thank you both for your time this morning.
Really appreciate your insights on behalf of Business New Zealand and Export NZ.
Thanks.
Okay, we come now to Zespri.
Morning.
Chair and members of the committee, good morning, and thanks
for the opportunity to appear today.
My name is Rachel Lynch, and I'm the Government and Community Affairs Manager at
Zespri.
Zespri strongly supports the India Free Trade Agreement Legislation Amendment
Bill and efforts to pass it before the election so that New Zealand kiwifruit
growers can access the benefits of the free trade agreement from the next selling
season next year.
India is one of the world's largest and fastest growing consumer markets.
Zespri has operated in India for more than a decade, and demand for
kiwifruit has continued to grow, driven by increasing consumer
awareness of health and wellbeing and rising disposable incomes.
During the last sales season, New Zealand exported around
7,500 tonnes to India, generating $32.7 million
in sales revenue. Despite that growth, our exports have been
constrained by the 33% tariff,
and the FTA changes that. The tariff will be eliminated within a quota
of 6,250 tonnes from day one, growing to
15,000 tonnes over six years.
Volumes outside the quota also benefit from a reduced tariff of
16.5%. For our growers, that's a huge
improvement in access to an important trade market and allows us to
allocate more fruit to India and build that demand over time.
And crucially, the quota is a foundation, not a ceiling.
So Zespri will continue to allocate fruit based on demand, and
long-term market opportunity, including above-quota allocations where
that supports our market development.
With clear execution, strong partnerships, and investment in the market, we
hope and aim to see further improvements in access over time.
And that matters because we're in an incredibly challenging trading environment.
Improved access and greater certainty are more important for exporters than ever,
and the opportunity is substantial.
With 1.4 billion people, even a fraction of those would be a
whole lot of new consumers. And over time, India has the potential to
become one of our largest markets, but that will take time and depend
on careful execution.
Our written submission, as you would have seen, focuses on part four of the bill,
which sets out the framework for the kiwifruit tariff quota system.
We support the framework in part four and the appointment of our regulator,
Kiwifruit New Zealand, as the quota manager.
And we also appreciate the way that MPI has worked constructively with
industry to design the allocation methodology and system.
The key points of that submission are pretty straightforward.
Firstly, we support MPI's decision to reduce the new entrant
allocation from 5 to 2.5%. We see that as a
commercially viable volume for a new entrant while allowing, to
maximize the value return to New Zealand growers.
Secondly, we support the fair allocation and hand-back dates, including the 15
July hand-back date for those exporters who aren't able to use the full
quota allocation.
Those predictable dates are really important given the commercial realities of the
season,
and make sure that New Zealand Inc.
uses the quota that we have to the full
benefit for all New Zealanders. Third, we
support the quota volumes being reported in tonnes and ask that the
regulations include a clear and consistent conversion to tray equivalents,
which is our industry standard.
Fourth, we seek two modest amendments to the legislation itself.
We ask that the quota manager's allocation processes are explicitly
required to be cost-efficient, and the review process for allocation decisions
should be affordable and timely given the commercial realities of the season.
And finally, I want to briefly address the Kiwifruit Action Plan.
This is a cooperation program funded by New Zealand growers
and delivered by our partners from BSI, our
Bioeconomy Science Institute, and developed with a collective industry
approach to support India's emerging green kiwifruit
sector, which is counterseasonal to our own, meaning that the fruit
is in market at broadly different times.
The program relates only to green kiwifruit.
It does not include New Zealand providing any plant variety right material,
and there is no transfer of protected commercial
know-how. Protecting IP and plant variety rights was built
into the program from the start, and it's a key part of why our industry is so
supportive of it.
The program is already underway with the development of two centers of excellence
in Nagaland and Uttarakhand, training being delivered to growers
and extension staff, and technical streams being planned and rolled out
for nursery, orchard, and post-harvest systems.
Just to note too, the operating environment in these regions is
challenging. The terrain is difficult, very
mountainous, there are roading constraints and very limited post-harvest
infrastructure.
In our view, the Kiwifruit Action Plan shows how improved market access
and practical industry cooperation can work together.
It supports local green kiwifruit growers in India, helps us get
more Indian consumers buying more kiwifruit year-round,
and protects New Zealand's IP and PPS.
In closing, Zespri strongly supports the bill.
We support the overall framework in part four and ask the
committee to recommend a small number of targeted amendments reflected in our
written submission.
We acknowledge and thank the officials involved in the negotiations and
implementation work and ask that the focus is now on passing the
legislation so that growers can benefit, uh, in the
2027 selling season.
Thank you, and I welcome the questions.
Excellent. Thank you, Rachel. Questions for Zespri? Dr David Dalton.
Yeah. Thank you very much for your submission, and also
congratulations on the success of the industry. It's just unbelievably good.
Thank you.
Looking forward to this. Obviously, my question's going to be about the Kiwifruit
Action Plan that you're-
Oh, sure
... investing.
And, we're looking to provide training
For growers, nursery. And obviously, cultivars will be part of that because
they're the green kiwifruit, correct?
There's currently a green kiwifruit industry in-
Yeah
... India right now. The only plant material that is
included in the program presently is rootstock-
Right
... which is not PBR.
Right.
And we've got just over 100 plants that BSI is
getting ready to send over.
And thank you also for your assurance that we're protecting gold and red.
I know that's very important. Yeah.
It's the
why our industry, again, is so supportive of this too.
Yeah.
Okay, thank you.
Very good. Rachel, I'm just interested if you could perhaps expand a little on your
views around the need to be cost efficient-
Mm
... or to be proportionate-
Yeah
... with the cost recovery piece and how you would define that for us.
Sure.
Kiwifruit New Zealand is already our regulator and has an obligation
to provide services to the industry that are cost efficient.
So we would just like that reflected, again, in
the legislation here. And in terms of being timely,
we need quick decisions in our industry.
The commercial realities are that volumes can change week by week.
So we would want to have,
in the legislation, an acknowledgement that any decisions as things
change would need to be both timely and cost effective-
Mm
... just so we can allocate and reallocate them as quickly as we need
to.
Okay. So just on that timeliness, a note under the
Clause 51, which is the process around reviewing a
decision to cancel or suspend an export license.
Mm.
There's a timeframe in there for anyone wanting to have a review of
decision made against them.
Mm.
Then there's a review of that, which
is not a prescribed timeframe, and then there is an appeal mechanism which is
prescribed again.
Mm.
So I'm interested in whether you feel that there should be a
timeframe for the review process as well, because obviously that
would enable a potential reallocation of-
Mm
... supplies if that review was not
successful.
Perhaps that's something that would be better in the regulations as we figure out
the realities of how that would work in practice, rather than have
it in the leg, which is harder to change if we discover that things don't quite
work as we thought they were going to.
Mm.
Okay. So across all of those as that review piece
in terms of the original complaint, the review, and
the potential-
Yeah
... appeal, that would be better prescribed in regulations-
I think so
... all three of those?
Yeah.
Okay. Thank you. Vanisha Walters.
Thank you, Mr. Chair. And mine is actually a supplementary-
Mm
... in relation to the cost-efficient provision.
Mm.
Appreciate that there's clarity in having it in primary legislation.
We also have regulatory impact assessments-
Yes
... which require that cost/benefit analysis as well.
And so that will apply to all secondary legislation.
Mm.
And I'm just wondering whether that is,
in terms of legislative harmony-
Mm
... an easier way of ensuring all our secondary leg-
... has that cost/benefit assessment which currently happens, and that way we're
not putting it in primary legislation across the board.
Sure.
Yeah.
That could potentially-
Cover it
... we're just wanting to-
Make sure it's there
... confirm that it's covered. Yeah.
It's a good point to raise.
Thank you.
All right, any further questions?
No, that's good.
Wonderful. Thank you very much-
Thanks so much
... Rachel, on behalf of Kiwifruit.
Okay, next up, we have Sovereign.
Good morning.
Yeah, hi, Tim.
Joining us-
Yes
... on behalf of Sovereign.
Thanks, Tim.
Wonderful. Thanks.
Yeah, my submission will address Clauses 47 and 66
and the treaty obligations that they activate.
This bill enables ratification, and ratification activates every provision that I
will reference.
First, just a foreword on what I think are the committee's shortcomings from the
first round of oral submissions and their report to Parliament.
The committee's treaty examination report failed to examine the Motu report's trade
diversion finding. It addressed Annex 8K, but dismissed submitter
concerns, stating that it will not change immigration flows in the ways that
submitters think they will,
without acknowledging Article VIII (3) (4) , which says that those
ICT visas are uncap able.
That provision also prohibits caps on labor market
tests and salary floors, which the UK has,
but they were also inundated with Indian visas under a
very similar ICT visa scheme. We don't have the ability to cap those.
MPs then relied on that incomplete report to justify their votes, while their
own representations in Parliament omitted the same critical details.
This bill hearing is the last opportunity to put on record what the treaty
examination report missed. Every step of this process has
been designed-
Mr. Riley, this process-
Yeah
... now is actually about the legislation in front of us to give effect
to the-
Sure, sure. I understand that. Yeah, yeah
... the comments need to focus around the legislation and stuff rather than the
treaty process.
Yeah.
This was import-- Yeah, I just thought this was important context because Sovereign
doesn't feel that the committee did a thorough job at reporting to Parliament what
the treaty actually does to New Zealand.
So yeah, I'll just start with Clause 47, which is the quota
on horticulture,
on kiwifruit, apples, and honey.
This clause creates quotas on horticulture exports to India, which are
conditional and suspendable Clause 47, as I
said, creates the quota systems for apples, kiwi fruit, and honey.
Annex 2B.9 of the FTA says that India alone can
suspend the access. So we're setting up legislation that didn't exist before.
This is new legislation, and it is conditional on an
action plan that is not yet in place.
The legislation and the FTA relies on several things
being set up, which includes cultivar transfer to India.
We have to set up centers of excellence and set up PVR framework.
And we just heard Zespri speaking to their confidence
in the IP protection that India will give us,
but none of that was stipulated in the FTA.
It just says that New Zealand needs to work with India to set up their IP.
And that's because India,
they're not a UPOV member. Zespri only trades with UPOV countries.
They haven't traded with India because they are not a UPOV member.
That's International Protection of Premium Varieties.
We expect that
India will do something in regards to IP to amend
this, but nothing in the FTA required that.
So we have
about a quarter or more of our trade, which is horticulture, and it is totally
contingent on India setting up an IP framework that's
compatible with New Zealand. It's also contingent on the transfer of our cultivars.
Zespri also mentioned BSI's work.
BSI said that India will be able to produce
10 times their current kiwi production given our skills and
the cultivars that will be transferred in the FTA.
So we're creating a massive competitor, a country that is known on the
USTR list to be a
priority watchlist member, alongside Russia, China, and
Venezuela for IP violations.
So we're setting up legislation, and we're
going to activate these provisions of the FTA, which do not protect at the
moment New Zealand's IP and our horticulture.
That is the heart and soul of our horticulture industry.
It's the development of our germplasm, our cultivars, and our premium
varieties over decades, and at a cost of about $100
million thus far.
Then we'll go to Clause 66, which is the Immigration Act commitments.
This clause enables Annex 8K, which I mentioned before, I referenced.
This is the uncappable pathway. This is the intra-corporate transfer
visas. Specifically, the specialists have no cap.
The treaty says that we cannot place caps on these visas.
The
committee looked at that and said, "We're not too concerned about it."
But they failed to understand that ICTs in this
treaty are very similar to ICTs in the UK.
Those ICTs were exploited prolifically,
and the UK had to clamp down. They did so by increasing
the salary minimum for these visas.
New Zealand doesn't have that ability, and the FTA specifically prevents us from
putting salary caps. So when the committee says that we're not concerned
because similar provisions are in other FTAs, they don't
understand that we are dealing with India, a country known for
exploitation of visas in the UK and in the United States.
That means we've got a country of 1.4 billion people that
we open the door to specialist transfers.
We have no ability to put the same levers in place that the UK used
to stop the exploitation of the very similar type of visa in the UK.
I believe that the committee needs to look at this closer, and by enabling Clause
66, they enabled this door through the 8K visa into New Zealand.
And then I'll just go to the FDI commitment that Zespri also
mentioned just before me. Or it was the submitter just before her,
actually. The FDI commitment is $20 billion
into New Zealand in 15 years. And last time I addressed this committee,
I asked if anybody knew the total outward FDI commitment to all
countries worldwide combined up to this date, and
that number is 16 billion. And I said it's impossible for New Zealand
to achieve the $20 billion FDI commitment.
And the committee went to MFAT, and MFAT agreed,
yes. It said specifically that New Zealand
cannot invest $20 billion into India, but that that's
only a promotion. So if we're agreeing to
promote $20 billion into India, a number that MFAT says is
not possible, which I backed up in my last oral
presentation, what are we doing? How can we prove to India that we
have promoted an unachievable amount of investment into India?
That is so abstract. And so now everything that this FTA
gives us, which is the tariff concessions, that's all we get.
We give India our cultivars, we give it our
$20 billion. The only thing we get back are tariffs.
Those tariffs are contingent on this FDI commitment, which is
largely undefined. India alone decides whether or not we met that
commitment. They take our tariffs, the entire FTA falls apart.
All of our investment up to that point is garbage. It's wasted.
And then there's a five-year review.
So after five years, India can come back and say, "Oh, did you meet the
FDI commitment?"
If we don't, there's another review after three years and three years for
eternity. So what company is going to continue investing into India if our
tariffs are clawed back at the first 15-year check?
We will never reach that
goal. And this hands India sole discretion over this FTA,
sole discretion to take back our tariffs. I think that's an oversight.
If somebody came to you and had a similar deal for
you to purchase something, you would say absolutely no, this is ridiculous.
But for some reason, this committee pretends like this is normal and this is fine.
And I think the committee needs to understand that they serve the country first and
not their party leader and not their party.
It is the country first, and this is not in New Zealand's best interest.
This is negotiated directly against New Zealand.
We have no cards in this game.
Any questions?
All right. Well, thank you very much for hearing your perspective on that.
Are there any questions for Mr. Riley?
No. Mr. Riley, you may wish to look at Article
14A32C and 5B,
which speak clearly to the protections around IP that may be useful
to address some of your concerns.
Well, but yeah.
Thank you very much for your time online.
Can I just
write a reply to that? The protect-
No, you've already said that they're not protected.
Those clauses clearly state they are, so-
I want to explain why those clauses don't protect-
We appreciate your time.
Why would you... I still have a couple minutes. I think I'd like to finish off.
And we will move on to our next submitter.
He barely has time. Can he respond to
what you've just said?
No.
No,
we're at time. We're at time.
Our next submitter, Rex Landing.
Thanks, Rachel.
Do we hear from Stanley?
It's Max Marshall, but I've bumped you.
I'm not sure who's on next.
Potentially, what have we?
We might have to wait for Watson.
Okay.
Watson Reynolds.
So we had Rex Landing, next then Metals New Zealand.
No?
Just the updated one is-
Oh, it's updated as-
Is Craig Atkinson?
Yes. Craig was-
Craig's not on yet.
Craig was on the side.
So Max Marshall.
Max Marshall is next, and then it would be Metals New Zealand, who we also don't
have. But we do have Cody Quince in the Zoom.
All right. Well, let's proceed there.
Okay, Cody Quince
online.
Yeah,
okay.
Good morning.
You can hear us all right, can you?
Morning.
Yes, we can hear you.
Can you hear us?
Yes, thank you.
Wonderful.
Yeah.
Okay. Thank you for bringing your time forward a little bit.
We have received your written submission and supplementary
contributions to that, and we'll hand over to you for five minutes.
Thank you.
I'm adding to my written submission today because I believe critical
new evidence has come to light. I think official advice
evaluated these trade clauses in isolation but
missed how they interact in the real world.
To fix that, I put together an independent risk audit using
financial modeling, a high court insolvency records,
and public trade data. I have formally
provided your secretary with a 100-page
strategic risk dossier containing 24 detailed
risks alongside with a suggested
statutory clause.
I
cannot go over all 24 risks in five minutes, so
I'm focusing on
one of the biggest structural risks I've found
and the exact fix the committee can adopt to
solve it.
I urge you to read the dossier in your
own time and
adopt the total control certificate as
suggested in the
clause provided.
First, public data shows our growers are carrying record
debt. Bank debt with Zespri SunGold
license prices previously peaked over
800,000 a hectare.
Crown officials call Chapter 9's 33
billion investment target aspirational, but
India's commerce
minister treats it as a strict baseline.
That
is why Chapter 9 includes a mandatory five-year review
clause.
It isn't a polite check-in, it's an enforcement
milestone. If New Zealand fails to send
2.2 billion in outward capital to
India every single year, that five-year review
gives India the leverage to pull back tariff
concessions.
When private capital falls short, the
pressure snaps straight back onto the debt-burdened growers.
Second, financial pressure drives foreign syndicates to
bypass buying sensitive land outright.
Instead, they build unscreened control
over our critical export infrastructure
through commercial leases on industrial
land, taking over pack houses,
cool stores, and port storage in separate sub
$200 million deals,
like Seeker
$60 million acquisition of OPAC
because
industrial land is not classified as a sensitive land.
The Overseas Investment Office screens
zero
of these commercial leases.
This lets foreign entities aggregate control
over strategic supply chains without
checks
Local Kiwis have to follow.
The risk model shows
that when an unscreened setup
collapses under debt, like the Baines Group
in Tauranga or Kiwi Crunch going through
owing $20 million, Section
248 of the Companies Act triggers
a complete lockdown of our export corridors.
Landlords are locked in. Property owners are
legally barred from
collecting rent or
re-leasing their pack houses while stuck in
liquidation court. Growers are locked out
of
Zespri contracts,
cold stores lock down, and fruit rots at the
port during peak harvest.
The terms-
All right. We've come to the end of your
submission time this morning. We appreciate your insights. Thank you.
Thank you.
Okay, next up we have Max Marshall.
Morning, Mr. Marshall.
Good morning.
Welcome back. You know how the process works, so I'll hand straight over to you.
Okay, thanks.
Good morning. Thanks for allowing me to have the opportunity
to speak.
I'm not going to labor what I've said in my submission.
I am concerned over what is on offer in terms of a trade-off for
us.
My submission follows a discussion rather than
a definitive account.
If I thought what the purpose of trade was
or what it should be about, it is about
lifting the standard of living for both countries involved.
Though with India's inequality, both structural and
class,
it is both more unclear how it is
achievable for them.
I believe that it is the market context that
ascribes everything
about the exchange. These trade deals are
market segmentation, which are business to business,
and this may mean that the benefit for the citizens, this may not be
passed to them,
but to the international investor of these companies.
The logic of true quality of life
interests of the people must be front and center in
any decision.
Certainly today, many
operations that are involved in primary industry
seem entirely corporate than the traditional
farmer operator. Trade deals in the 21st century is not so
much about different nation states, but
more about facilitating exchange between the different business entities.
I do not deny that economic activity defines the
landscape in which all other institutions, including the
apparatus of statehood, must operate.
I want to say that we, the public, have been asked to accept
the supposed benefits of a deal
on scant
information, much less approval of a foreign
leader who is blank.
We are familiar with a single market buying all of our
primary goods. My grandfather was a dairy farmer during the
'60s and '70s
on a
return servicemen
resettlement farm, selling his milk and butter to our historical
partner, and I myself grew up on a kiwifruit orchard.
I wonder if we're not trading in on one paternal
partnership,
which was
a bit one-sided for another.
There are other opportunity
costs from this deal. Why, instead of selling primary commodities,
are we not investing in other economic multipliers, the
service sector, technology, pharmaceuticals, et
cetera?
The fact of our geographical isolation can be a barrier, but
also an advantage in others.
The shipbuilding capacity afforded by our huge sea territory remains
a deeply untapped opportunity.
In a borderless economy, the working of the market has a reach and strength
beyond anything that Adam Smith could ever imagine.
My question is not so much
with trade. Yes, we need foreign currency, but who are the
beneficiaries
at the end of the day?
Therefore, the proof of the pudding will be at the end of the day if it
translates into real benefit in terms of lifting the standard of living for
people living in New Zealand.
Excellent. Very good. Any questions for Mr. Marshall?
Can I just say thank you. It's a very good submission.
Oh, thank you.
And you raise some interesting questions that I think we all
need to go through, but do you accept that
actually trade is beneficial generally-
Yes
... for the progress of the world?
Absolutely.
And so
you raise some issues, but it's hard to know what is the particular point
of most
concern to you in this trade agreement.
It's the-
Benefit in terms of where the wealth
is going to end up.
I was in Melbourne last week and I visited
Box Hill, and that has a huge
Chinese diaspora. And I
think that's successful because
I saw families and this generational wealth,
whereas I see
with corporations, you're
having the wealth transferred
overseas. And
simply, a
person who comes here and wants to live
here and contribute to the country,
I support that.
Let people come here and make money.
But it's less tangible if
I looked at the
neoliberal context, which says
you
financialize
all of your industries.
Right. Thank you very much, Mr. Marshall. Appreciate your time.
Okay, we move now to Metals NZ. Joining us online,
I believe.
Okay, we should have
Rick Osborne and Mark Taylor, I believe.
Can you hear me? Can you see me?
Yes.
Wonderful.
Excellent. All right.
Some IT issues. Not one of my strengths, but we've got there.
Classic.
Thank you very much.
All right, no problem. I'm sure you're aware how the process works.
We'll hand straight over to you for your 10 minutes.
Thank you. Thank you. Morning, よ い よ tatou, Chair, members of the committee.
Thank you for the opportunity to appear on behalf of Metals New Zealand.
I'm Rick Osborne,
CEO of Metals New Zealand, and joining me is Mark Taylor, the founder,
former CEO and Metals board member of Framecad.
I'll briefly outline potential challenges arising from the agreement before Mark
highlights the opportunities it creates for an advanced manufacturer like
Framecad. We'll then open up for your questions.
Fundamentally, Metals New Zealand supports the New Zealand India FTA and the
legislation implementing it.
However, our support rests on a simple principle,
free trade must also be fair trade.
As the Honorable Damon O'Connor penned in a recent NZ Herald op-ed,
it's important to consider how this agreement affects New Zealand core productive
sectors.
As a small trade-dependent economy, New Zealand's prosperity relies on free, open,
and rules-based trade.
India is one of the world's fastest-growing major economies, and this agreement
presents significant opportunities for New Zealand exporters, manufacturers,
and consumers.
Our manufacturers are highly competitive when markets operate on a genuine level
playing field.
We compete through quality, innovation, service, not through subsidies,
unfair trade practices. For that reason, we welcome
the inclusion of the transitional safeguard provisions in the bill.
They provide an important safety valve should increased imports cause
injury to domestic production.
This is particularly important to New Zealand steel and aluminum sectors.
India is now the world's second-largest steel producer, manufacturing
150 million tons of steel annually, compared with New Zealand's
production of circa 650,000 tons.
They even have a minister of steel, maybe something for members to aspire to in
future governments.
This scale creates opportunities for our infrastructure and construction
sectors while also reinforcing the importance of robust safeguards
should unfair trading practices emerge.
The same applies to New Zealand's aluminum extrusion industry, which provides
critical manufacturing capability for construction and infrastructure while
supporting regional employment.
And as the Chair no doubt knows, many of these are located in the mighty Waikato.
Maintaining these industries strengthen New Zealand's economic resilience,
supports lower emissions manufacturing through recycling and local
production,
and help ensure secure domestic supply chains during periods of
global disruption like COVID-19 and the recent issues in the Middle
East.
We encourage the government to continue strengthening New Zealand's trade remedies
framework. Effective enforcement, timely investigations,
and adequate resourcing are essential if businesses are to have confidence
that trade rules will be applied fairly and
consistently. It is equally important that imported products
continue to meet New Zealand's product safety and robust
seismic standards. I'll now hand over to Mark to speak to
Framecad.
Thanks for the opportunity to share our commercial experience.
Framecad is a high-tech manufacturer based in New Zealand.
95% of our earnings come from overseas,
and I established the business 38 years ago.
The India market is an interesting market for us.
We were first in it 16 years ago. Currently, we're competing against
products from all regions, including India.
And currently, our duty rate is 7.5% more
than what it is from
China competitors. So the free trade agreement will help at least start evening out
the playing field in terms of the higher duties we
face going to the country.
So for us, we're also developing technology specific to the
market. We have a next generation of equipment coming out
which matches the market requirements of India, and we're launching that product
in four weeks' time. We have a strong market presence.
Our team are traveling to India again next week.
So anything we do to open up the lines of trade and
remove barriers that disadvantage us to other
countries is interesting for us.
And so we see this as a positive development.
And we're also working with New Zealand Trade and Enterprise to help grow the
market there. So for us, it's an important market for the future, and
overall, out of all world markets at the moment, we see it's probably got the
highest growth potential. It could have up to
300% growth potential for us.
Mm.
So there's not many markets
where the trend towards new forms of construction, the
need to do housing, schools, hospitals,
commercial projects and infrastructure is massive in India.
And so we've got technology that helps do rapid construction, and that's why it's
a massive opportunity for us.
Thank you, Mark.
Just in closing, Metals New Zealand supports the passage of the bill.
We believe it strikes the right balance in opening new opportunities with a key
trading partner, while preserving the safeguards and trade remedies needed to
ensure fair competition and protect New Zealand's strategic manufacturing
capability. I'll now open up for questions from the committee.
Wonderful. Thank you, Rick and Mark. Appreciate that.
I just had a question on that growth, Mark.
That would be a phenomenal achievement, 300% growth.
What timeframe are you envisaging that's potentially available
over?
I think over the next two or three years.
Wow, okay.
It's a market that's been a solid market for us.
We're developing both the right technology for the market to how they'd use
technology over there. The other thing we're also doing is currently work with
Waikato University on creating one of the best courses on
how to design engineer for our applications in the world.
Of those, 55 engineers attend that course this year,
most of them are Indians
coming here to learn about New Zealand know-how and technology and engineering.
Mm.
But also, yeah, so at the moment we're exporting education to India .
I think the next stage is we have a lot of interest from large companies like Tata
Steel for us to help set the standards for industry there,
plus transfer knowledge over there, how to use our technology in India.
Okay. Next question, Dr. David Wilson.
Yeah. Look, thank you Rick and Mark. That was a really good submission.
I enjoyed it. And Mark, your experience in market, I think
is really valuable. And you mentioned some of the barriers.
Could you give us an idea of what you think those are and how
we may be,
if you like, addressing those through the FTA?
At this stage, the duty reduction is obviously one barrier, which is
helping us get closer to our competitors.
The market is a market that we're trying to do
technology and awareness transfer.
So fortunately, we're about to apply for support from
NZTE for market growth grant there.
The challenge for New Zealand is actually to get known up there.
It's a very large market.
Many, many languages
.
Mm.
So yeah,
we're looking to employ
at least three people up there that even speak the different languages around
India. So it's a very significant opportunity, the world's most
populous country with a massive need for rapid construction,
but still a challenging market to service logistically to create the
awareness and
even payment methods out of India aren't that easy.
There is some banking arrangements, I understand, direct to the UK with Standard
Bank. But in the future, even if there's more direct banking arrangements,
to take friction out of doing business, each of these things that slows us
down slows the growth process.
Yeah. Thank you very much for the insight, Mark.
All right. Any further questions?
All right. Thank you very much, Rick and Mark.
Appreciate your time, and very exciting to hear the opportunity ahead of you.
Thank you for the opportunity. Much appreciated.
Thank you.
Okay, we come now to Jesse Cuthbert.
He's not online.
Not online?
We've got Luke Walloth online.
Okay, we'll go to Luke Walloth then. Thank you. Online.
Sorry, is Jesse gone?
Apparently so. And,
John William.
Okay.
John.
Luke is online.
Hello. Can you hear me?
That's right.
All right.
Yes, we can. Can you hear us all right?
Yes, I can hear you just great. Pleasure to be here.
I only had a couple of hours to go over the documents, but
I know it's not relevant to
the specifics of today, but I did want to say I do second all of Joshua
Riley's concerns. I did see his presentation about
visa exploitation and IP exploitation.
But moving on from there--
Sorry, one second.
Under Section 59, I found particularly
interesting, it says
under the offenses,
"Liable for a conviction of a fine not exceeding $200,000."
And then again, subsection 1D is liable on conviction to a fine
of 10,000. Subsection D
is the offense of intent to deceive, give
false or misleading information, or make material omission
when requested to provide information under this part.
Why would you give a smaller fine when someone
is intending to break the rules? Would you not be
incentivizing
exporters to do a cost-benefit analysis on breaking the law versus
profits made?
Is that
something worth thinking about? Or I guess
my question is,
why would you punish someone less for intentionally breaking the law than
accidentally breaking the law?
Okay. Mm.
Okay. Something to think about.
All submissions are something to think about, Luke, absolutely.
Sure. Okay.
So appreciate you sharing your thoughts on that.
Of course, there are
costs involved with the quota
managers. They need to be paid when doing their job
and whatever costs involved.
As a New Zealand consumer, we
pay international prices in a global market.
So let's say we sell
a kiwi fruit for a dollar overseas, it's going to cost a dollar here.
That's just the way the world works.
That's why we can import cheaper, lower quality
American butter, because we produce better quality butter that
fetches a better price overseas.
So the point I'm trying to get to is, if there's going to be
an increased cost of production for the
people who are given the export licenses under the
quota manager system that's being proposed and
ultimately managed by the minister,
how much will that increase prices domestically for things like
the milk and kiwi fruit that we're exporting?
Is that just going to increase my grocery bill at the end of the day?
That would be
just something I noted,
thought about. And
given the high rates of,
I'll just say it, given the high rates of corruption and fraud in India,
will the minister/ministry in New Zealand be able to
audit Indian quota managers and holders, or can only the Indian
minister audit Indian-based quota managers and Indian
quota-
... quota
holders? Do
we have any means to audit what is going on at the other end of the
trade once our product has left the country?
I think you said that there before, that there was some provisions
made for that, but I would be
wanting to know if there was a specific New Zealand representative that would be
able to do that.
Something else to also
take into consideration is the
auditability of the supply chain. Yes.
And lastly,
this is a question from my mother, which I thought was quite good.
Besides the Trump tariff tantrums, is this trade agreement done under
duress and pressure from the new anti-China alignment found in both
Republicans and Democrats in the US, resulting in us trying to look
for new trade partners and moving away from China?
Pardon me.
Sorry.
That's it.
Okay. Very good. Thank you very much, Luke. We've got time for a quick question.
Dhanushi Walters.
Thank you, Luke. I just thought I might be of help in terms of
Clause 59, 2A and B, and the different penalties
that you mentioned. So the first-
Yeah
... the first three offenses are focused on the offender
themselves. The last one looks to me like it's
focused on what I would call an accomplice, so not
the offender. So if you had someone who was exporting ,
then they would be charged under one of the first three, but if you had an
associate, they would be charged under the fourth one, which is why you have the
lower penalty.
Okay. All right.
Intent.
Why would you maybe not
take away their export license if they're caught breaking the rules?
They can't play. Just,
yeah, that's all. That's all I'd have to say about that.
Yeah. All right. No, valid points. Appreciate that, Luke.
Thank you.
Thanks for identifying those for us.
Appreciate
it.
Thank you.
Cheers.
Thanks.
Okay. We move now to Peter
Grant online.
You'll
just have to
get him to turn on his camera and microphone.
Okay. Peter, you'll need to turn on your camera and microphone, please.
Move.
Okay. I think you can see and hear me now, can't you?
Yes, we can.
Okay.
Excellent. All right. Looks like a beautiful day out there.
And straight over to you for comments.
Yeah. It's absolutely lovely. I'm on my boat.
Which I'm
trying to-
Oh, sick.
It's raining today, actually.
Oh, that's good.
Stop it. I don't think we've had a submitter from a boat before, so this is good.
How good.
Fire away.
Okay.
The Indian FTA is an appalling deal for New Zealanders for so many
reasons and for so little benefit.
It has been drawn up in a totally untransparent way with no
scrutiny by an independent body. Our politicians have
been repeatedly dishonest about the contents of the FTA,
misleading the public and not allowing enough time for submissions and feedback.
There are contentious clauses in this FTA that have
no place in a trade agreement, nor would they survive a
vote in Parliament. It appears that the government is using this
FTA to install unpopular
regulations without due process.
For instance, the commitment to central bank digital currencies,
sneaking it in after the public have said no.
Uncapped immigration channels, which are going to make it even harder for
Kiwis to get a job, put more stress on our housing.
And why does this deal require New Zealanders to invest
around $35 billion into India?
This is an impossible target and will make the deal
unworkable.
This would massively reduce our investments into New Zealand.
UNDRIP. What the devil is the UN Declaration on the
Rights of Indigenous People doing in there?
And giving India our cultivars of high-yield kiwi fruit
and apples, then training them on how to grow them
has
got to be the definition of economic insanity.
This will be a-
Mr. Grant, sorry. We've already completed the examination of the treaty itself.
These hearings are around the legislation to give effect to that.
So, if you'd like to speak to that legislation, then we'd welcome your views
on it.
Well, I think the legislation is
not
following due process.
From what I understand, it has not,
and will not, be voted on properly in Parliament.
And I think this is an appalling lack of
representation of the people's will.
There hasn't been good feedback, good submissions,
good accountability of what's going on, or
awareness of the contents of the deal, and it's
appalling that Parliament don't get to vote on
these things. They only get to vote to say, "Yes,
go ahead," but they don't really
vote on the contents, and the deal has been secret.
So, I think it's a betrayal of New Zealanders, this deal, and it should
be restarted with an independent body
to scrutinize
all aspects of the deal at the negotiation stage and report
to Parliament, and the Parliament vote on their report.
All right.
Well, thank you for sharing your perspective on that.
Rest assured, this is going through the normal parliamentary process, so there will
be votes on all aspects of it. Any questions for
Mr. Grant?
Have a good day.
All right. We will let you get back to your beautiful day out on the water-
Yeah
... and hopefully catching some fish.
Thanks for your time.
Yeah, thanks very much.
Cheers.
Have a good day. I hope you follow due process.
Okay, right.
We come now to Rex Landy.
Good morning.
Kia ora. Good morning.
Thank you.
All right, we've received your submission. You know how the process works.
We'll hand straight over to you.
Thank you. Do not ratify it.
This is information from your economic impact assessment performed
by Treasury.
The economic impact assessment paper is using models,
guesses, just like COVID, it was guesses.
Now, the GDP raise in 2027 is going to be
127 million from this deal.
That is 0.03% of our GDP.
The GDP raise in 2036 is going to be
382 million, and that's
0.07% of our GDP.
And in 2050, it's going to raise to 657.7
million, which is 0.1%. So, all the benefits
don't even raise our GDP by even one percentage
point. Not even one. I'm not an economist, but that
seems a bit
sus.
Tariff eliminations are the way these increases are made, not more exports
or quotas.
89% of 2027's GDP raise is
by tariffs. No other economic benefit to New
Zealand, but tariffs. 63% of
2050's GDP raise will be via tariffs.
They'll take one to 10 years to implement.
This is a quote from it, "Tariff reductions are the largest source of New
Zealand GDP increases in all years, but the share of the increase is
due to tariffs decreases over time."
And in the same report-
Ms. Landy, we've already heard you.
Yes.
We've already heard your views on the content of the FTA.
Yes. And these, yes, this is about the law-
Today's hearing is about the legislation itself
... and you are en-
Talking over you
... Yes, it's about the law too.
And so we'd appreciate your views-
It's about the law that you're going to put in
... on the legislation.
Yes, and the legislation that you are enacting is putting
this in place when we have not even had a decent
say for it. These are real wages increase for all workers,
especially production workers,
0.06% and
0.098%.
Now, these mechanisms that you are putting into place to install
this, this was made by people, we weren't
even given a say or even to put any input in.
No public view was put in
for this. I would like you to cap the student numbers and remove any
provision within the free trade agreement about bringing people
here. It's a free trade agreement, not a free human trafficking agreement.
It's not-
Do you have any insights on the legislation?
Yes.
Okay, please come to those.
Recolonization by another name.
That's all it is. And to-
Ms. Landy, we need your insights on the legislation.
Well, I'm telling you-
If you don't have any of those, then we'll move on
... the only thing missing from this law is lube, as we're bent over.
Thank you.
Okay. All right. That's us done.
Yeah.
We don't need those sorts of comments.
Okay.
All right. Now, we have two remaining submitters.
We are
running a bit ahead of time for the moment, seeing there's been some slight
issues.
So we might just suspend our live
hearing
now,
and then we can look at turning to those two submitters
at their time. So, we'll suspend the li-